<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the great antidote of Paracelsus, Van Helmont, Croulius, and by them called the elixir proprietatis shewing the true way of preparing of it, and the wonderfull cures they have performed thereby. And also this authours experience thereof. Written by J. H. a lover of truth, and made publique for the good of all that stand in need thereof.</title>
            <author>J. H., lover of truth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H81A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221259</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832593</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832593</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37067</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45620)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2146:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the great antidote of Paracelsus, Van Helmont, Croulius, and by them called the elixir proprietatis shewing the true way of preparing of it, and the wonderfull cures they have performed thereby. And also this authours experience thereof. Written by J. H. a lover of truth, and made publique for the good of all that stand in need thereof.</title>
                  <author>J. H., lover of truth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the authour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Guildhall Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paracelsus, 1493-1541 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Helmont, Jean Baptiste van, 1577-1644 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Croll, Oswald, ca. 1560-1609 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Therapeutics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37067:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37067:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE Great Antidote OF <hi>Paracelſus, Van Helmont, Croulius,</hi> And by them called THE Elixir Proprietatis Shewing the true way of preparing of it, and the wonderfull Cures they have performed thereby. And alſo this Authours Experience thereof.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>J. H.</hi> a Lover of truth, and made publique for the good of all that ſtand in need thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Authour, 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37067:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37067:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, I have here ſet before thee the opinions of theſe great Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, concerning this incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Medicine, pardon me if I have not ſo fully explained their meaning as poſſible thou canſt wiſh; If this finds exceptance with thee, then expect ſuddenly a large diſcovery of this nature; in the mean time give me leave to tell thee, there is no cure mentioned in my Experimentals, but I am able to give a ſufficient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count from credible people; to name them; it's poſſible, would be to ſome prejudicial therefore I omit it; and I will aſſure thee that I have been a diligent Searcher into the ſecrets of things for the finding out of good Medicines two Apprentiſhips, and could never find a ſurer or ſafer nor more effectual Medicine than this. If thou benefit by it, thank God, if not, blame me. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe in</hi> Crouched-friars, <hi>at the Sign of</hi> John Baptis Van Helmont <hi>near</hi> Tower-Hill.</dateline> 
               <signed>J. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:37067:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aracelſus</hi> in his Archidoxes, hath theſe words, <hi>R.</hi> Myrrh, Alloes, Safforn, of each a like quantity,<note n="*" place="margin">A Veſſel ſo called.</note> put them in a Pelican well cloſed two months in a ſand Furnace, with a gentle heat, after put the matter in a Limbeck, and Diſtill over the Oyle without burning, circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late this Oyle for a Month, and after keep it for uſe.</p>
            <p>He ſaith that the virtues of all natural Balſams, are in this one Medicine contained, and that it doth above any other Medicine keep back old Age; he adds further, that the Age of a man will be too little for the diſcovering of all the virtues therein contained.</p>
            <p>That great Philoſopher <hi>John Baptiſt van Helmont</hi> in the 458. <hi>page.</hi> preſcribes this way of making of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> Myrrh, Alloes, Saffron, of each an Ounce, being beaten, put them into a large Glaſs with a long neck,<note place="margin">Commonly called Boulthed.</note> cloſe the neck of the Glaſs, and put it in a gentle heat for fear of breaking the Glaſs, let it ſtand until you ſee a cleer Oyle circulate, then break the neck of the Glaſs, and poure on a pint of Cinamon water, and Diſtill it in<note n="*" place="margin">Putting the Glaſs in boyling water.</note> 
               <hi>Balneo</hi> till no more will aſſend, then keep it for uſe. This Medicine, ſaith he, cures the obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Lungs, called Aſthma, the Convulſions, the Appoplex, Palſey,<note n="*" place="margin">Deadly Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connted by the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</hi>
               </note> Atropha *Tabes, all Agues, and (ſaith he) a man that had taken the holy Sacrament, and the extreme Unction, being ſo far waſted with the third day Ague (which is the ſhame of Phyſitians) was ſo far cured by this Medicine in ſo ſhort a time, that I dined with him the next day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Crollius</hi> in 250. of his <hi>Baſilica Chyomica,</hi> or Royal Receipts, <hi>R.</hi> Myrrh, Alloes, Saffron of each four Ounces, powder them, and put thereon ſo much *Alcalizate Spirit of Wine, as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37067:3"/>will reduce them to the form of paſte, then put ſo much Oyl of Sulphur made by a Bell ſtill as will colour the matter black, then pour on Spirit of Wine tartarized 4 fingers over, put them in digeſtion two dayes, ſeparate the tincture, then pour on good Spirit of Wine, and circulate it two months, ſeparate the tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and deſtil the fecis by a gentle heat.</p>
            <p>The firſt Spirit that comes over add to the tinctures, and (ſaith he) it will be far better then the common diſtilled for the virtues of it, he hath the words of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> and adds further, that it moſt powerfully aſſiſts nature againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes that old ages bring, removing the obſtructions of the Lungs and Cheſt pipes: prevents popular Infections, and Infectious airs, and Peſtilential Feavers, removes all peſtife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous humours in the Stomach and Bowels, and eaſes all pains there: Takes away the obſtructions of the brain, curing the<note n="*" place="margin">Turning in the head ſo called.</note> Virtigo,<note n="*" place="margin">A pain in one half of the head.</note> Meagrim, the dimneſs of the ſight, comforts the memory, prevents the Palſey, and Gout, quickens the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects and all the ſenſes, breaks the Stone in the Reins or Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, comforts the Heart, and expels Melancholly, and takes away that intollerable pain in the Belly, called the <hi>Illiaco paſſio,</hi> carries away Salt humours inſenſibly, and all ſurfeits from intemperance of Dyet or Drink, cures the third day Ague, and the Hectick Feaver, and brings forth congeiled blood, and ſpeedily heals inward Ulcers and Wounds; further, ſaith he, all Diſeaſes proceeding either from heat or cold, this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine doth by an occult property heal.</p>
            <p>Having formerly ſeriouſly conſidered of theſe Authours, I find <hi>Van Helmont</hi> in the 626. <hi>page,</hi> not only to find fault with the preparation of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> but alſo not to ſeem to follow or allow his own middle way, as he calls it; but ſaith, that it is beſt prepared by a Diſſolvent. Now of Diſſolvents there is two, according to his and <hi>Paracelſus Doctrin;</hi> the great Diſſolvent, as they call it, is the <hi>Alkaheſt,</hi> of what it is made of, or how, neither mention. The other is the volatile Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> volatiſed with Spirit of Wine, of which <hi>Van Helmont</hi> gives a large account, where he ſayes that in unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spirit of Wine with the Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> that of one
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37067:4"/>Pint of <hi>Aqua-vitae,</hi> is made half an Ounce of Medicine, the reſt in the Conjunction is converted into his own Element of Water; and ſaith he, that which is done with the volatile Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> is equal to that which is done with the <hi>Alkaheſt,</hi> onely this, that the <hi>Alkaheſt</hi> is ſeparated from the Medicine by Diſtilling, and the volatile Salt of <hi>Tartar</hi> remains united to the Medicine: Now <hi>Crollius</hi> his tartarifyed Spirit of Wine ſhould be that volatile Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> and I ſhould like his preparation was his Oyle of Sulphur left out, for that is an Albortive in Philoſophy, and ſome other ſmall errors he hath there, in which my paper will not now give me leave to ſpeak of, for I am tyed to two ſheets: I ſhall now tell you how I prepare it, and what virtues I have found by it in this term of years ſince I was Maſter of it; my way is this, <hi>R.</hi> Myrrh, Alloes, Saffron, of each four Ounces, bruſe the Myrrh and Alloes, and put them into a boult head, with the Saffron, poure thereon a pint and half of volatile Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> volatified with ſpirit of Wine, according to <hi>Helmont,</hi> which he and <hi>Paracelſus</hi> call <hi>circulatus minor,</hi> ſet it in an aſh Furnace, with a gentle heat till the ingredients be fully diſſolved, and the bitterneſs and gummouſneſs be fully gone, a few earthly fecies will remain in the bottom, which ſeparate and keep the ſpirit for uſe. This <hi>Elixir</hi> thus prepared, will in colour reſemble the pure ſound Arterial blood of a Healthy man, and in ſmell and taſte will be very pleaſant, in which the Myrrh and Saffron will plainly appear, only their bitterneſs will be gone, and in ſtead thereof a pure fragrancy remaining. This Medicine thus prepared, is that which I have had experience of for ſome years, for which I owe eternal thanks and praiſe to Almighty God: for had I not had this, (though I have many others by which I have performed many excellent cures) yet for all them, I had not been here to have writ this, for in the height of the Sickneſs in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1665. I was taken with a Lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy with that violence, that for the ſpace of ſeven dayes I could take nothing but drink, my drink was ſometimes Sack, and ſometimes Ale; ſometimes I was ſenſeleſs for many hours together, and when I recovered my ſenſes a little, I did ſtill
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37067:4"/>call for and took this Medicine, and by Gods bleſſing on it, was perfectly cured, though it was reported with much confidence, that I was both dead and buried, and by no incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable perſons neither, and at the ſame time all my Family was moſt dangerous Ill, my Son, a Child of eight years old, was taken with an Impoſtumation in his Neck near the jugular Vein, which Diſtemper he had two years before in the ſame place, when formerly coming out of the Countrey, was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with it the next day, and now by reaſon of my illneſs, I could not ſo mind it, but that it came to a ſuppuration, and I being a little recovered, was much troubled to ſee, but in ſhort time brought forth the matter and healed it, and ſince he hath continued well. My daughter of the age of ten, had a Blane on her Breaſt, but did not keep the houſe four dayes for it. My wife had a Peſtelential Feaver, but was cured of it in three or four dayes, though in the beginning of the Feaver, by taking this Medicine, there came forth many Feaver Spots, and the Nurſes ſeeing them, did conclude ſhe had the <hi>Tokens,</hi> and it was talked publiquely abroad, that I had cured her of the <hi>Tokens,</hi> which thing I abſolute deny to be within the reach of any Mortal Man to cure the real <hi>Tokens,</hi> though there are many ſorts of Spots not much unlike, which are as eaſily cured as the Diſeaſe they proceed from, as Surfeit Spots, Purple or Scurvy Feaver Spots, and ſuch like; but the <hi>Tokens</hi> are, I am confident, Marks ſent from God, and it is as impoſſible to cure any that once have them, as to contradict the Divine Decree; and beſides my own Family, many came to me both in my ſickneſs, and before and after, ſo that there was not a day during the Viſitation, but from Viſited houſes, and ſome that had running Sores, came daily to me, which I no more refuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then the ſoundeſt and healthieſt bodies, nor ſhall not God willing upon a juſt occaſion, nor to Viſit a Friend or Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the greateſt of Dangers, for I have ſeen many that have had many Sores &amp; Blanes, ſome that have had the <hi>Tokens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thoſe that had Riſings, I alwayes adviſed them to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the Riſing with Oyle of Lillies, and Oyle of <hi>March</hi> Mallows, of each a like quantity; and if they broke, as ſome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37067:5"/>did, then to apply onely that Oyntment called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Apoſtolorum,</hi> and any Playſter to keep the Lint that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent was on to the Sore, and to take daily this Medicine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, according as I ſhall afterward direct. So doing they have been perfectly cured by Gods aſſiſtance and this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, and never troubled any Chyrurgion, though ſometimes there hath come forth a large Core, Neither is this Medicine onely for this Diſeaſe, as the Authors mention and my own experience have found, for the greateſt part of my Practice hath been this many years, and is to this day, in thoſe Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers which are by the common Phyſitians accounted uncure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and I have wrought and ſtill do on many other ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients both Vigetables, Minerals, and Metals, and yet in all of them, I could never find neither ſo ſafe, nor ſo ſpeedily effectual a Medicine, as this one which being of a Solar nature (that is cordial) that as the Sun by his Beams removes all fogs and vapours from the earth, ſo this Medicine expells all venomous and obnoctious humours from the principle parts of the body, or as <hi>Van Helmont</hi> ſaith, paſſes to the Limen of the fourth concoction, removing all praeternatural coag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulations, though they never ſo obſtinately add here to the Veſſels, caſting them forth by Urin and Sweat for it is ſo generall a cleanſer of the blood, that had I not ſeen the effects, I ſhould not have believed it, for I have applyed it both to perſons in Pleuriſies and Quincies, and in one hour the party hath been left perfectly at eaſe going to ſleep, and in their ſleep have been in a ſmall ſweat, and have waked well, not loſing one drop of blood, as the common cuſtom is.</p>
            <p>The like have I done by the Squincy, and in Feavers, of which I can verifie, the ſaying of <hi>Van Helmont</hi> in the 458. <hi>page. Hoc medicamine tam quartanam quam continuam ſtatim abſolvi:</hi> For I have often cured a Feaver in two or three days; the ſmall Pox, which is a rotten putrid Feaver, I have cured in three dayes, the venom being breathed forth in a ſmall gentle ſweat and the party perfectly well, and not any of the Small Pox hath ever come to matter, though they have been before much ſwell'd with them; the Hectick Feaver, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37067:5"/>will not admit of bleeding without Death, is by this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine ſuddenly cured: The Convulſions I have frequently cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red even where there hath been no hopes of life according to common reaſon; and I do my ſelf, and adviſe all my friends to give of it to their Children, firſt after they are born, ſix drops in a Spoonful of Ale; and I have had ſeveral that have given me thanks, and I alwayes find the Child the better for it for a long time, and if the Mother of the Child take it ſo ſoon as ſhe is delivered, it will eaſe her of after pains, and prevent the vapors of the Mother, being taken for a few dayes night and morning in<note n="*" place="margin">Fear not the heat of the Sack for no Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will ever trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you if you take this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</note> Sack, faſting one hour after. I have had many Patients of the Muther-vapou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and been long in the curing of them, though I uſed the beſt means I could deviſe; but ſince I have made uſe of this Medicine for that ſad unquiet reſtleſs Diſtemper, I have found that a few dayes will cure it, except the party be old, and have had it many years, and then ſome longer time muſt be allowed, and by Gods bleſſing, you will not miſs your expected deſire. I cannot explain things as I would do, for want of paper; but I ſhall give it you in brief as plain as I can: and that I may do it more methodically, I will take the Diſeaſes of the Head not yet mentioned. The Diſeaſe of the head called <hi>Tutanus,</hi> which is the Subliming of an offenſive matter in the Brain, as whereby the ſenſes are ſuddenly ſuppreſt, one Doſe of this Medicine brings the party to their ſenſes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and being taken night and morning according to order quickly rids them totally of ſo unwelcome a gueſt. For the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey I have ſeveral times cured the worſt ſort of them, that is, the Palſey in both ſides; that in one ſide is but a trifle to the other, for in one there is but part of the Brain obſtructed, in the other it is all obſtructed. The Swimming in the head which is a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of Melancholy, is preſently by this Medicine cured. Many are, by reaſon of bruiſes, troubled with Impoſtumations in the head, which, after having taken this Medicine, do caſt forth much corrupt matter by the Noſe, and after become well, and ſometimes the Hearing is obſtructed, and ſometimes the Sight grows dull by reaſon of a foul humour in the Brain, which I find is much helped by this Medicine: And although I have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37067:6"/>Spirit of Eye-bright in the houſe, and Eſſence of Sullandine; yet I prefer this Medicine before both, for the dimneſs of the Eyes, which I, by much working in the Fire and Mineral fumes cannot avoid the often receiving dammage both to the Eyes and Brain. That Diſeaſe called the <hi>Tremor,</hi> I have cured in Fourteen dayes, when the ſhaking was ſo violent, that if you held the hand ſtill, it would force the body to move; and one thing I am to inform thoſe that are Lovers of Children, when a Child in the month is froward, either by reaſon of ſome crudities it received from its Mothers overmuch eating of fruit and traſh, or from hurt or bruiſe in the birth, or by reaſon of wind; then for ſome <hi>Diaſcordium,</hi> ſaith the Nurſe; and that, ſaith ſhe, is a harmleſs thing, and will bring it to ſleep: for, ſaith ſhe, it is peeviſh for want of ſleep, and then the Mother preſently conſents, though it proves the Childs ruine, for though they do not give it ſo much as contains ſo much Opium, as to cauſe it never to wake again, yet that little cold poyſon is the worſt of poyſons which will lodge in the body till it either brings the Convulſion fits, or, if the Child be ſo ſtrong of nature to paſs that danger, then after ſucceeds either the Rickets or a Weakneſs in the Limbs. Which want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge many after repent when it is too late. I had rather any Child of mine took Mercury, then half its weight in Opium, for I can ſpeak by experience of what I have ſeen in Children whom I have ſeen after they were born, &amp; what they are brought to by this error. Next, in the middle Belly that is incident to the Palpitation of the heart, and fainting fits, from a wind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Arteries, for which this Medicine is a preſent help. As for the Tabes, a Conſumption from a corruption of humour alwayes accompanyed with a Cough, this Diſeaſe flyes before this Medicine, as combuſtible matter waſtes by fire.</p>
            <p>I have at the writing of this, a Patient, which when he came to me had a great Looſeneſs, and no Stomach to eat; after being upon recovery, he by his own careleſsneſs in over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walking in the extreme heat, and drinking when he was hot, and lying on the ground, was again ſo bad, that he could not walk half a mile: but ſince, by the bleſſing of God on this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37067:6"/>Medicine, he can walk luſtily, and hath a reaſonable good Stomach, and what he eats diſgeſts well with him; and I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not but he will ſuddenly have no more need of my help. There happens many times a windineſs in the <hi>Pleura,</hi> that is a skin within the Ribs near the Heart, which by delayes proves dangerous, alwayes coming with a diſſiculty of breathing, which is by this Medicine removed preſently, and by taking of it three or four dayes together, is fully cured; the windineſs of the Stomach is preſently expelled by it.</p>
            <p>The Scurvy, a Diſeaſe ſeldome taken notice of by people till their Teeth drop out, or a Dropſie followes them, or the Jaundies; and then what will they not do to be cured. They that have any of the three, or two of them, or all the three, let them take this Medicine and it will rid them of their grief: but obſerve alwayes, the more Diſeaſe is plicated, the longer is required for to continue the taking thereof. Always obſerve, fixt Diſeaſes require the longer for the removing, and are for the moſt part in leſs danger of death. Many are the Diſeaſes incident to the lower Belly, as the Spleen, cauſing either a pain in the ſide or ſometimes ſending up vapours into the head, cauſing unquiet ſleep, makes thoſe that are troubled therewith to be peeviſh, produces Melancholy, it being the ſeat and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle of Melancholy. He or ſhe that takes this Medicine ſhall find a pain and tearing near the Spleen after an evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of much Wind downward, the Spleen being ſo near the Hypocondriacks, that ſeldome one is well and the other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, but commonly both together. I had a patient near ſix years agoe, that was in a deep Melancholy, that if he ſee any one laugh would be very angry: alwayes he deſired this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, after he had once taken of it, though he had others by: I have cured many Melancholly people, but by the taking this Medicine when the obſtructions opened, he broke ſo much wind backwards, that the neighbour at the next houſe wondred what noiſe that was; and after that, he was cured in a little time. That Diſeaſe the Seamen call the Belly ake, which in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> kills ſo many brave men for want of help, had they with them but a ſmall Glaſs of this, they might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37067:7"/>be thereby preſerved, for it would quickly remove that intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable pain, and ſend the cauſe forth at the back-dore; There is no Medicine in the world will ſute better with thoſe that go long Voyages to Sea, eſpecially into hot Countreys: for let them carry it to what part of the world they will, and keep the Glaſs cloſe ſtopped, it ſhall not loſe any thing of its virtues; for neither the heat of the Summer, nor coldeſt froſt that is, wil take any more impreſſion on it then on a ſtone: That which will not preſerve it ſelf, cannot help to preſerve another: Thoſe that have the Muther-fits, if they take but a doſe of this when they find the Fit a coming, it will prevent it. All ſorts of Fluxes is by this Medicine cured, ſometimes a Looſneſs and Vomiting is cauſed by reaſon of a cake of Worms, which is alwayes accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed with much Flegm: this Medicine breaks the bed of Worms, and leaves the Patient fully recovered, though few but have therewith a ſtrong Feaver, which is cured alſo. There is a Diſeaſe which is called <hi>Lupus Phlegmaton,</hi> but by many fooliſhly taken for the Dropſie Tympanities, the Belly being ſwelled to a great bigneſs, by reaſon of a cake of congealed flegm. I had this Spring a Gentlewoman of near 50 years in this Diſtemper, and taking this Medicine three weeks or a month, found little alteration, but then did begin to be looſe, voiding much flegm; the next day ſhe vomitted and was looſe and the vomitting, continued for two dayes, and every day came from her many Baſons full of flegm, and at the end ſhe ceaſed both vomiting and looſeneſs having voyded that which was the cauſe of her Diſtemper: during all the time of her Illneſs, ſhe ſtill continnued taking this Medi- and now is happily rid of her Diſeaſe. This Medicine is both a great cleanſer and ſtrengthner of the Spermatick Veſſels in men or women, thereby begetting fruitfulneſs in both Sexes; for it doth ſearch every corner of the body, and caſt forth what ever is offenſive to nature. Some years ago, there came to me a woman big with Child, whom her Husband had given a Clap; and I did not onely cure her of it during her going with Child, but alſo the Child: ſo that when it was born, it was as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37067:7"/>fine a Child as you ſhall ſee, and did thrive as well for ſome years: but I hear both the Mother and the Child dyed in the Viſitation. The Difficulty of making water doth ariſe from ſeveral cauſes, as from wind, from the ſtone, and from a ſlimy matter furring that paſſage of the Urine; and ſometimes by a carnoſity of the three firſt, I have had experience and find them eaſily helped by this Medicine: the Stone onely deſires a long time for the breaking, and yet I ſent ſome five years ago this Medicine to a Perſon of quality, and in Fourteen dayes after they ſent me word that it had ſo broken the Stone, that there had come away too ſpoonfuls of Sand every day, for a long time; and when there was no more left, there was no more to be expected. Now whether this was the Stone in the Kidneys or Bladder, I know not; for the Patient was a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miles from me: but this I do not queſtion, but it will as well reach the Bladder as the Reins; for I once applyed it to a perſon that had an Ulcer in the neck of the Bladder, a man of near fifty years old, there was a tumor betwixt the Scrotum and the Fundament, they boch being broken before I knew it, ſo that the Urine came forth there every time he made water, and alwayes in making water he had a great ſmarting in that place, after, as well as before the irregular paſſage of the Urin was ſtopped; yet I could find no Medicine that he found ſo much good by: but in ſhort time he was by this perfectly cured, without the leaſt obſtruction in making water, although it brought away much mattery ſubſtance during the time any thing of corruption remained there. The ſymptoms by which you may know the Ulcer in the Bladder or the neck of the ſame, are a pricking pain after making water in the end of the yard in men, and in woman in the paſſage of Urin: ſometimes there comes away a mattery ſubſtance with the Urin, ſometimes like hairs will appear in the Urin, ſometimes both, ſometimes a ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in making of water: and when there is nothing of the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Diſeaſe, when theſe ſymptoms appear, then you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude there is an Ulcer either in the Bladder or in the Neck of the ſame: and in outward Ague-ſores, I have ſeen its effects, for being taken inwardly without ever applying any thing out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37067:8"/>but a ſcorch'd rag, the ſores have run till the matter hath been fully taken away, and they have healed of their own accord: the Patient taking this Medicine daily till they were fully healed, after hath continued well many years, and I queſtion not but moſt ſores may be ſo healed, and the moſt venomeſt of Ulcers, Cancers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be made by the taking of it more apt to heal, for as they do proceed from a venomous humour, ſo this Medicine doth expel the greateſt of venoms. For when I have been by accident in Mineral fumes that will poyſon any man to continue in, I have taken no other Antidote againſt them. I confeſs I never tryed it againſt poyſons, but do verily believe, it will moſt potently expell any ſort of poyſons, it will ſo ſpeedily remove peracute Diſeaſes: the Dropſie will flye before this Medicine for the Liver being freed from obſtructions and the Urinary-paſſage, nature will do the reſt, unleſs it be accompanyed with a Conſumption, and then there is but ſmall hopes of a cure. The Piles, a diſtemper much following Melancholy people, and oftentimes that ſort called the blind Piles, which alwayes with a vehement pain and burning, as though fire was in the place, by the taking of this Medicine, it doth much mitigate the pain and by degrees takes it fully away, but doth not fully ſtop the bleeding Piles, for that is the ſink of body, and would be much injurious. Ruptures called Broken Bellies, which proceed from wind or water, this Medicine doth ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily take away. A Rupture, is a wind in the lower Bowels cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an extention of the <hi>Peritonaeum,</hi> and in men and boys the Bowels extending the Kall, ſo that they fall into the <hi>Scrotum</hi> or Cod; and the obſtructions of the Bowels being removed, the Diſtemper hath no place to lurk in. I have had them that have had this diſtemper ſome years, and then I ahve cauſed them to wear a Truſſe; and I ſhall alwayes chooſe a Steel-Truſſe before any other, it being well made and fitted. But what need I ſpend ſo much time and paper in mentioning particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; ſince there is no Diſeaſe that I have met with, but this Medicine will cure: for I find that the obſtructions being open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and the parts ſtrengthened, there can remain not any thing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37067:8"/>of a Diſeaſe in any part of the body. Now I ſhall direct how I alwayes order the taking of it, my advice is to take it Night and Morning in a glaſs of Sack, and faſt one hour after, but not longer. In the morning, the quantity to a ſtrong body, threeſcore drops, to a Child new born ſix drops, to one of a year old ten drops, of four years old twenty, and to one of twelve years old forty; alwayes obſerving that ſome are as ſtrong at ſix years, as others at ten, and then the doſe is to be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Thoſe that take it againſt Infections, need not take above twenty drops, and only in the morning, unleſs they go where infected people are, and then it is neceſſary to take it as often as they come where danger is. Sometimes it will be needful for thoſe that have the infection,<note place="margin">If they take it out of order it will do no harm though but little good.</note> and have had it a day or two before they take it for them, then to take it four times a day, in the morning, and at ten before noon, and at four afternoon, and at night. Thoſe that are taken either with Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie, Quinſie, or any other peracute Diſeaſe, let them take it ſo ſoon as the Diſeaſe appears, and if the firſt Doſe doth not move it to their minds, then let them take it again two hours after; alwayes putting themſelves into bed ſo ſoon as they have taken it: and if they be dry, let them drink as much drink as they will in reaſon deſire; but alwayes I forbid them ſmall beer: it being of a crude quality requires the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, and ſo hinders the operation of the Medicine; but thoſe that are not lovers of ſtrong beer, let them mix Sack with their ſmall beer, and they will find that the leſs quantity of drink will allay their dryneſs: I omitted in my preparation to tell you that my <hi>Tartar</hi> that I make my Salt of is red, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Raymund Lulley</hi> in his <hi>Teſtamenta nova,</hi> where he teaches the making of the <hi>Mercury</hi> of the Philoſophers: Now a word or two to my Brother <hi>Tyro,</hi> let me adviſe thee when thou goeſt about any Chymical preparation, firſt to learn to know the three-fold Salt in nature, the three-fold Sulphur, and the three fold Mercury; and the ſympathy and antipathy in them; their ſeparation and union; and the cauſe of their not uniting the degrees of heat and cold required for their putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: underſtand theſe, and then thou mayeſt be in hopes of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37067:9"/>accompliſhing ſome part of thy deſire: for if thou faileſt in any of them, thou wilt loſe thy labour.</p>
            <p>A word to thoſe that take this Medicine: be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e they take it, let them ſeriouſly conſider whether they can have patience in fix'd Diſeaſes, to continue the taking of it, as in old ſettled Griefs will be required, and if they cannot, I deſire them to let it alone: if they will take it, then let them in the firſt place deſire a bleſſing from God on it, and then queſtionleſs they ſhall obtain their deſire; and having obtained their deſire, let them return thanks to God for it; alwayes concluding they that receive any thing of good, and not giving thanks to God for it, do but rob God. For order in dyet, let the Patient eat what is moſt agreeable to the Stomach,<note place="margin">The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuſis is the beſt Schoolman in dyet.</note> alwayes obſerving that the Stomach better knows what will agree with it, then the Doctor doth. For perfume againſt infectious airs, I alwayes had Red Saunders and Roſmary of each a like quantity, and do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it beſt, as the one comforting the heart, the other the Brain; and this I prefer before that commonly made with Brimſton and Niter, which burn both Cloths and Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings where ever it comes. I could eaſily prove it Inimical to nature: but I ſay no more leſt Mr. <hi>Whiteaker</hi> raile againſt me, as he doth againſt <hi>Van Helmont</hi> for ſpeaking truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Elixir truely prepared, is to be had at this Authour's houſe in</hi> Crouched-Fryers <hi>near</hi> Tower-hill, <hi>at the Sign of</hi> John Baptiſt Van Helmont: <hi>the price of a whole Glaſs is five Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and a half Glaſs two Shillings ſix pence; and at Mr.</hi> Rad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords <hi>in</hi> Queen-ſtreet <hi>near the</hi> Blew Bell; <hi>in</hi> Weſtminſter-hall <hi>at Mr.</hi> Gavills, <hi>the Sign of the</hi> Faulkon, <hi>and at Mr.</hi> John Playford<hi>'s Shop in the</hi> Temple. <hi>Sealed with the three Lyons Rampant,</hi> and no where elſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37067:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
